Guide to the William M. Nichols Papers 1914-1966
Montana Historical Society Archives
- General Correspondence
  - Taylor B. Weir, 1946-1956 (Box-folder 7 / 19)
  - U.S. Senator Burton K. Wheeler, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 7 / 20)
  - David White Sales Company, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 7 / 21)
  - Talbot Wildman (Wildman and Company, liquors), 1946-1950 (Box-folder 7 / 22)
  - Conrad L. Wirth (National Park Service, including possible sale of hotels), 1948-1957 (Box-folder 7 / 23)
  - Wood, Struthers and Company (includes James Marshall, Cornelius Bliss, A. Oakley Brooks), 1946-1954 (Box-folder 7 / 24)
  - W (correspondents include Rollin D. Weary, Martha Weathered Shops, Albert B. Wells [uncle], William Wiggins, Wilcoxson's Confectionery Company, Winterthur Museum, Dean Witter, U.S. Representative Charles A. Wolverton), 1946-1957 (Box-folder 7 / 25)
  - Yellowstone National Park, Yellowstone Park Church Committee, Yellowstone Park School Board, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 7 / 26)
  - Yew Char, 1946 (Box-folder 7 / 27)
  - Young Men's Christian Association [YMCA], 1952-1956 (Box-folder 7 / 28)
  - Y (correspondents include Yale University, Robert M. Yoder, Dan Young), 1946-1953 (Box-folder 7 / 29)
  - Trudy Zabriskie, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 7 / 30)
  - Z (correspondents include Captain William J. Zalesky, Zion's Cooperative Mercantile Institution [ZCMI]), 1946 (Box-folder 7 / 31)
- Diaries
  - Diaries (re daily schedule of activities, persons met, weather, etc.), 1933-1945, 1947-1954 (Box-folder 8 / 1-9)
- Financial Records
  - Audit reports: Child and Anceny [Flying D], 1914-1923, 1927 (Box-folder 9 / 1-4)
  - Audit reports: Flying D Ranges Inc., 1930-1942 (Box-folder 9 / 5-6)
  - Audit reports: Gallatin Gateway Townsite, 1931, 1935 (Box-folder 9 / 7)
  - Audit reports: La Jolla Company, 1941, 1949 (Box-folder 9 / 8)
  - Audit reports: Salesville Mercantile Company, 1922 (Box-folder 9 / 9)
  - Balance sheets: J.D. Veach Company, 1924 (Box-folder 9 / 10)
  - Dividends from Yellowstone Park Company stock, 1951-1955 (Box-folder 9 / 11)
  - Employee bonus lists: Yellowstone Park Company, 1946-1956 (Box-folder 9 / 12)
  - Expense accounts for travel, 1946-1957 (Box-folder 9 / 13)
  - Expense distribution, 1948-1954 (Box-folder 9 / 14)
  - Insurance, 1947-1954 (Box-folder 9 / 15)
  - Inventories: liquor, 1947-1956 (Box-folder 9 / 16)
  - Invoices [scattered], 1946-1957 (Box-folder 9 / 17-18)
  - Invoices: Yellowstone Park Company (primarily wine cellar), 1954-1956 (Box-folder 9 / 19)
  - Salary as Yellowstone Park Company president (pay check stubs), 1943-1955 (Box-folder 9 / 20-21)
  - Taxes: gift tax, 1949-1954 (Box-folder 10 / 1)
  - Taxes: income (William M. Nichols and Ellen Dean Child Nichols), 1945-1957 (Box-folder 10 / 2-14)
  - Taxes: income (Ellen Dean Child Nichols), 1958-1966 (Box-folder 10 / 15-16)
  - Taxes: Property (Broadwater County: Wild Cat claim), 1955 (Box-folder 11 / 1)
  - Taxes: Property (Gallatin County: Spanish Creek Ranch [Flying D]), 1945-1959 (Box-folder 11 / 2)
  - Taxes: Property (Lewis and Clark County: Helena house), 1919-1957 (Box-folder 11 / 3-4)
  - Taxes: Property (San Diego County, California: La Jolla house), 1926-1929, 1945-1957 (Box-folder 11 / 5)
  - Taxes: Property (San Mateo County, California: Hillsborough house), 1946-1955 (Box-folder 11 / 6)
  - Taxes: Social Security on household employees, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 11 / 7)
  - Miscellaneous (includes Yellowstone National Park expenditures; income distribution from Nichols/Child companies; La Jolla Company), 1935-1955 (Box-folder 11 / 8)
- Legal Documents
  - Miscellaneous (includes purchase of property in Hillsborough, California; sale of portion of trust property by Ellen Dean Child Nichols to John Q. Nichols), 1937, 1953 (Box-folder 11 / 9)
- Subject Files
  - Automobiles (re licensing, maintenance, etc.), 1946-1957 (Box-folder 12 / 1-3)
  - Birth certificates (correspondence about obtaining certificates for several family members), 1957 (Box-folder 12 / 4)
  - Bricker Amendment (re foreign treaties), 1953-1954 (Box-folder 12 / 5)
  - Burglaries of Helena house, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 12 / 6)
  - H.W. Child Corporation (holding company; includes information about the management of the company, investment of its funds, and its subsidiary companies), 1931-1962 (Box-folder 12 / 7-11)
  - H.W. Child Corporation and Yellowstone Park Company reorganization plan, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 12 / 12)
  - H.W. Child Estate, 1946 (Box-folder 12 / 13)
  - H.W. Child Trust (trust fund set up to benefit descendants of Harry W. Child; it was major stockholder of H.W. Child Corporation), 1935-1955 (Box-folder 12 / 14-15)
  - H.W. Child Trust (trust fund set up to benefit descendants of Harry W. Child; it was major stockholder of H.W. Child Corporation), 1956-1958 (Box-folder 13 / 1-4)
  - Huntley Child, Jr., 1938-1942 (Box-folder 13 / 5)
  - Maria Dean Foundation [re investments of], 1957-1958 (Box-folder 13 / 6)
  - Dishwasher (re purchase and maintenance), 1948 (Box-folder 13 / 7)
  - Bessie Ferguson House (7958 Prospect Avenue, La Jolla, California), 1950-1962 (Box-folder 13 / 8)
  - 555 Fuller Avenue Building Corporation (audit), 1955-1960 (Box-folder 13 / 9)
  - Hugh Galusha (accountant), 1951-1955 (Box-folder 13 / 10)
  - Gardiner Townsite (re real estate holdings; includes materials of Harry W. Child), 1920-1940 (Box-folder 13 / 11-14)
  - Gardiner Townsite (re real estate holdings), 1941-1964 (Box-folder 14 / 1-8)
  - Gardiner Townsite (lot register), 1920s-1960 (Box-folder 14 / 9)
  - Gardiner Townsite (maps and plats), 1933-1947 (Box-folder OvFd / 1)
  - Vernon Goodwin (partner in Yellowstone Park Company and its predecessors), 1941-1948 (Box-folder 14 / 10-11)
  - Vernon Goodwin Estate (Margaret Goodwin), 1954-1958 (Box-folder 14 / 12)
  - Vernon Goodwin, Jr. ("Ted"), 1955-1959 (Box-folder 14 / 13)
  - Newell Gough, Jr. (re Nichols family business affairs), 1957-1966 (Box-folder 15 / 1)
  - Green Meadow Farm (Harry W. Child; also includes Elliston Farm [Camp Child]), 1923-1930 (Box-folder 15 / 2)
  - Green Meadow Farm, 1931-1944 (Box-folder 15 / 3-7)
  - Green Meadow Farm (maps), 1922, n.d. (Box-folder OvFd / 2)
  - C.A. Hamilton; Hamilton Stores Inc., 1928-1945 (Box-folder 15 / 8-10)
  - C.A. Hamilton; Hamilton Stores Inc. (includes joint operation agreement), 1946-1955 (Box-folder 16 / 1-2)
  - Fred Harvey, L.W. Scott (includes report on operation of Yellowstone Park Company), 1960-1961 (Box-folder 16 / 3)
  - Jack Ellis Haynes (re photograph business), 1937-1956 (Box-folder 16 / 4-5)
  - House at 705 Harrison Avenue, Helena, 1956 (Box-folder 16 / 6)
  - House at 1802 Floribunda, Burlingame, California, 1953-1956 (Box-folder 16 / 7)
  - Insurance, 1954-1957 (Box-folder 16 / 8)
  - Investments, 1934-1944 (Box-folder 16 / 9-10)
  - Investments, 1945-1952 (Box-folder 17 / 1-4)
  - Investments: Ellen Dean Child Nichols, 1952-1956 (Box-folder 17 / 5-6)
  - Investments: William N. Nichols, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 17 / 7)
  - Investments: William N. Nichols stamp collection, 1932-1944 (Box-folder 17 / 8)
  - Investments: stocks and bonds held by H.W. Child Corporation, H.W. Child Trust, Spanish Creek Ranch, Yellowstone Park Company, William M. Nichols, and Ellen Dean Child Nichols, 1955 (Box-folder 17 / 9)
  - Investments: records of stocks, bonds, etc. (small ledger books), 1922-1961 (Box-folder 18 / 1-2)
  - Leases (correspondence, legal documents, etc., re lease of state land), 1922-1927 (Box-folder 18 / 3)
  - E. Herrick Low (re finances of the various companies), 1957-1965 (Box-folder 18 / 4-7)
  - Clara Quintard Nichols Estate, 1937-1946 (Box-folder 19 / 1-5)
  - Ellen Dean Child Nichols, 1954-1966 (Box-folder 19 / 6-8)
  - John Quintard Nichols, 1947-1956 (Box-folder 19 / 9)
  - William M. Nichols (death; includes sympathy cards, obituaries, etc.), 1957 (Box-folder 19 / 10)
  - William M. Nichols Estate, 1957-1962 (Box-folder 19 / 11-13)
  - William M. Nichols Memorial Fund (at Mammoth chapel; includes lists of contributions by employees), 1957 (Box-folder 19 / 14)
  - William M. Nichols military record (World War I), 1917-1919 (Box-folder 19 / 15)
  - Charles E. Perkins (correspondence with Harry W. Child), 1923-1930 (Box-folder 20 / 1)
  - Anna K. Pryor (Pryor Stores), 1934-1952 (Box-folder 20 / 2)
  - Spanish Creek Ranch (Flying D Ranges; managed by Archie Martin), 1929, 1942-1948 (Box-folder 20 / 3-10)
  - Spanish Creek Ranch (Flying D Ranges; managed by Archie Martin), 1949-1962 (Box-folder 21 / 1-9)
  - Spanish Creek Ranch (Flying D Ranges; maps; architectural drawings of alterations of Vogel Ranch House), 1954, n.d. (Box-folder OvFd / 3)
  - C.P. Tomlinson (re his contract to try to sell Yellowstone Park Company), 1951-1958 (Box-folder 22 / 1-7)
  - Taylor B. Weir, 1939-1947 (Box-folder 22 / 8-10)
  - Taylor B. Weir, 1948-1956 (Box-folder 23 / 1-5)
  - Taylor B. Weir (re proposed legislation), 1948-1949 (Box-folder 23 / 6)
  - Western Hotels Inc. (re possible purchase of Yellowstone Park Company), 1961 (Box-folder 23 / 7)
  - George Whittaker (Yellowstone Park Store; architectural drawing of gas station in OVERSIZE FOLDER 4), 1934 (Box-folder 23 / 8)
  - Wood, Struthers and Company (C.N. Bliss re investments), 1951-1957 (Box-folder 23 / 9)
  - Wyoming Yellowstone Park Commission (re proposal to purchase Yellowstone Park Company; includes correspondence; report of Duff, Anderson, and Company; clippings), 1955 (Box-folder 23 / 10-12)
  - Yellowstone Park Company, 1950, 1958-1962 (Box-folder 24 / 1)
  - Yellowstone Park Company (re financial holdings), 1952-1964 (Box-folder 24 / 2-3)
  - Yellowstone Park Lines, 1938-1960 (Box-folder 24 / 4)
- Miscellany
  - Adelaide D. Child deed to La Jolla property; will, 1939, 1945 (Box-folder 24 / 5)
  - Humorous stories, etc., n.d. (Box-folder 24 / 6)
  - Itineraries for William M. Nichols and employees' travel, 1948-1956 (Box-folder 24 / 7)
  - William Ford Nichols will; memorial edition of The Pacific Churchman, 1921, 1924 (Box-folder 24 / 8)
  - Notebooks; address books, n.d. (Box-folder 24 / 9)
  - Isaac Quintard will and codicils, 1856-1882 (Box-folder 24 / 10)
  - Veratina Oil Company stock certificates, 1901 (Box-folder 24 / 11)
  - "Who gets what" (if H.W. Child Corporation liquidated and Yellowstone Park Company stock sold), 1950-1953 (Box-folder 24 / 12)
  - Miscellaneous (includes Yellowstone Park Company stationery, Jack and Isabel Haynes greeting packet, Western Conference of National Park Concessioners meeting agenda, itinerary of Franklin D. Roosevelt visit to Park), 1937-1954 (Box-folder 24 / 13)
- Transfers
  - Lists of photographs transferred to the Photo Archives (Box-folder 24 / 14)